Wickham family papers MSS 15753
Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library
- Correspondence of John Wickham (1763-1839)
  - Edmund Randolph to John Wickham, 1812 January 14; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Requests Wickham provide the wording to a decree that would enable a sale of his property in Richmond, Virginia, to proceed since his power of attorney, Mr. Botts, was unable to perform his duties.
  - John Randolph of Roanoke (1773-1833) to John Wickham, copies of 2 letters, 1820; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Originals of these letters transferred to the John Randolph of Roanoke papers.
    One letter, March 24, 1820, incomplete, last page only, John Randolph of Roanoke writes concerning Stephen Decatur's death. In a second letter, April 1, 1820, part of the letter and autograph signature excised, John Randolph of Roanoke thanks Wickham for his indulgence and civility in the matter of his father's estate and mentions [Littleton Waller] Tazewell's move to Norfolk.,
  - Littleton Waller Tazewell (1774-1860) to John Wickham, 1819-1838; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Topics include: request for advice on a business proposition concerning property offered by Mr. Page as security for the payment of Tazewell's stock (July 4 and 9, 1819); Tazewell's current ill health (November 26, 1819); criticism of President John Quincy Adams and a description of a duel between Henry Clay and John Randolph of Roanoke (April 8, 1826); and damages suffered during a hurricane (October 14, 1838).
  - John Wickham (1763-1839) to William Richardson, 4 folders, 1798-1810; 4 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 14-17)
    Letters concerns legal work performed by Wickham for Richardson.
  - Family Correspondence – John Wickham to his wife, Elizabeth Selden McClurg Wickham (1781-1810), October 23; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Expresses concern over several outbreaks of cholera among citizens and slaves on the plantation.
  - Family Correspondence – John Wickham to his son, James McClurg Wickham (1802-1850), September 10; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Writes from White Sulphur Springs about the convalescence of Susan [Decatur Wickham (1819 -1831)].
  - Family Correspondence – John Wickham (1763-1839) with his son, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), 1817; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 20)
    John Wickham addresses business matters in his absence on a trip to Philadelphia, sending four letters from stops in Washington, Baltimore, New York and Philadelphia.
  - Family Correspondence – John Wickham (1763-1839) with his son, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), 1830; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 21)
    He discusses the prospects for the wheat crop, the demand for flour in [American] towns and South America, and reports on his conversations with Mr. Haxall about pricing if the crop is delivered early (May through August 1830) and the last letter mentions their pleasant stay at the Sulphur Springs and Sweet Springs and the journey home, the drought in Kentucky and Ohio, and "this new explosion in France" (September 24, 1830).
  - Family Correspondence – John Wickham (1763-1839) with his son, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), 1832-1834; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 22)
    Wickham writes to his son William F. Wickham with concerns about his wheat crop, a notification of an outbreak of disease at Howard School for boys from Jonathan Loring Woart, and the preoccupation of the Virginia General Assembly over internal improvements (January 29 and May 30, 1834); the design of a mill powered by water (February 21, 1834); discussions about the Bank of Virginia and the elections (April 17 and 21, 1834); discussions about possible schools for their boys and rumors of a duel in Washington (September 28, 1834); discusses the President's message (December 7, 1834); a slave sick with cholera who was believed to be dead several times, appears to be recovering partly due to work of Dr. McCaw (December 18, 1834); and politics in Washington (December 24, 1834).
  - Family Correspondence – John Wickham (1763-1839) with his sons, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), George Wickham (1816?-1841), and Littleton W.T. Wickham (1821-1909), 1837; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Wickham writes to his son William F. Wickham with concerns about his wheat crop (July 6, 1837) and to his sons at the University of Virginia, George and Littleton W.T. Wickham with advice about their studies, especially geology and the study of soils, and their visit to the Natural Bridge (May 15, 1837).
  - Family Correspondence – John Wickham (1763-1839) with his son, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), 1838; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 24)
    The letters written during a trip to New England by William F. Wickham and Anne Wickham mention seeing the effects of a great drought all over the northeast, speculations about the wheat crop, poor corn crop of the current year, Littleton at the University of Virginia and George reporting for duty in Washington in the U.S. Navy (September 13, 17, and 25, 1838); news about the wheat market and John Wickham's health (November 20 and December 12, 1838); and news about the opening of the [James River and Kanawha Canal] and its advantages for Richmond, Virginia (December 20, 1838).
  - William Wirt (1772-1834) to John Wickham, 1815, 1830, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 25)
    The originals of all three Wirt letters have been transferred to the Autographs collection.
    Wirt asks for Wickham's advice concerning the rights of the widow in the estate of John Ellis (December 21, 1815); in another letter, October 10, 1830, autograph signature excised, Wirt asks for his advice and support in the case of the Cherokee Nation versus the state of Georgia, argued by Wirt before the Supreme Court; and in a third undated letter, Wirt discusses a property case involving Colonel Byrd and Mr. Harrison of Berkeley and lots in Manchester and Richmond, Virginia.
- Correspondence of the Wickham and related families
  - Family Correspondence of Anne Carter Wickham Renshaw Byerly (1851-1939), 1866-1881; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes a letter from Robert E. Lee to his cousin, Miss Annie Wickham [later Anne Carter Wickham Renshaw Byerly], Lee promises to stop by "Hickory Hill" to visit if at all possible on his way back to Lexington, autograph signature excised from the letter (May 23, 1870).
    The original of the Robert E. Lee letter has been transferred to the Robert E. Lee papers.
    Biographical / Historical
    Anne Carter Wickham (1851-1939), the daughter of Williams Carter Wickham and Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham, married Robert H. Renshaw (1833-1910) in 1881 and they had four children. In 1920, Anne Renshaw married Dr. W.E. Byerly and lived in Massachusetts.
  - Family Correspondence of Anne Carter Wickham Renshaw Byerly (1851-1939) written from Port Oratava, Tenerife, Canary Islands, to her brother Henry T. Wickham, 1882; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Family Correspondence of Anne Carter Wickham Renshaw Byerly (1851-1939), with three letters from Robert H. Renshaw (1833-1910), 1883-1925; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Letters through March 1883 are written from Port Oratava to Henry T. Wickham but in April 1883 the Renshaw's began their journey home, settling in New Market and then Boyce, Virginia, by the turn of the century; In 1906, Annie writes from the University of Virginia about Robert H. Renshaw's poor health which continues until his death in 1910.
  - Family Correspondence of Lucy Carter Wickham Byrd (1834-1923) with her Aunt Anne Butler Carter Wickham, 1855-1868; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Lucy Carter Wickham Byrd was the daughter of Edmund Fanning Wickham (1796-1834) and Lucy Carter (1799-1835) and the wife of George Harrison Byrd (1827-1910).
  - Family Correspondence of Lucy Carter Wickham Byrd (1834-1923) with her Uncle [William Fanning Wickham], circa 1868-1880; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    These letters are chiefly undated, but she appears to continue her correspondence with her uncle after the death of her Aunt Anne in1868, chiefly written from New York.
  - Family Correspondence of Lucy Carter Wickham Byrd (1834-1923) with her cousin Lucy and others, circa 1859-1979; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Family letter of Robert Carter, consisting of a copy of a "letter of advice to my children," Will, Anne Lucy, and Thomas Carter, originally dated October 12-14, 1803 and copied into a notebook, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Family Correspondence of Charles M. Fry (1822-1892) and Elizabeth Wickham Leigh Fry (1824-1895), chiefly written from New York, 1872-1877, 1888; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Family Correspondence of Charlotte Wickham Lee (1841-1863), 1858, 1862; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Family Correspondence of Chapman J. Leigh (1826-1911), 1850-1878, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Family Correspondence of Julia Wickham Leigh (1801-1883), 1836-1865; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 11)
    One letter, September 16, 1836, described a duel between her brother James and John Chapman, which ended in reconciliation between the two men.
  - Family Correspondence of Julia Wickham Leigh (1801-1883), 1870-1878; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Family correspondence of Judith Nelson (1782-1869), 1852-1856; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Family correspondence of Lucy Nelson, 1857-1872; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Family correspondence of Lucy Nelson – one letter to Mrs. Anne B. Carter Wickham, concerning the death of Anne's sister, [Lucy] (oversize), 1835 January 19; 1 folder(s) (Oversize box S-69, Oversizefolder 5)
  - Family Correspondence of Julius Theodore Porcher (1829-1863), 1857-1863; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 15)
    Contains one letter, August 17, 1863, concerning the Civil War, from Chattanooga, Tennessee, shortly before his death following his wounding and capture.
  - Family Correspondence of Mary Fanning Wickham Porcher (1831-1875), chiefly written from Eutawville, South Carolina, and Walworth Plantation during the Civil War, to her Aunt Anne Butler Carter Wickham, 1854-[1868?]; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Family Correspondence of Mary Fanning Wickham Porcher (1831-1875), chiefly written to her Uncle William F. Wickham, 1872-1874; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Family Correspondence of Mary Fanning Wickham Porcher (1831-1875), undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Family correspondence of Samuel Porcher (1857-1944), one letter as a student at the University of Virginia (October 28, 1877), 1873-1877; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Family correspondence of Judith Page Walker Rives (1802-1888), 1829-1862; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Topics include the preparation to leave for France with her husband, William Cabell Rives, appointed minister to France (June 26, 1829); and their return to Paris, France (August 2, 1851).
  - Family correspondence of Henry Taylor (1827-1914), chiefly to his sister Lucy Taylor Wickham and General Williams Carter Wickham, 1861-1883; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Family correspondence of Julia L. Taylor, writing from "Belvidere," "Greenwood," and "West End" plantations, 1858-1879; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence of Mary Watson Taylor (1832-1905), 1875-1895; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Family correspondence of Thomas L. Taylor (1836-1901), 1853-1876; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 9)
    One letter, written from the Warm Springs Hospital, discusses Taylor's health problems and the recent Battle of Cheat Mountain (October 2, 1861).
  - Family Correspondence of Ann G. Thomas, 1861-1886; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Family correspondence of Anne Butler Carter Wickham (1797-1868), chiefly letters to Anne, 1823-1862; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Family correspondence of Credilla Miller Wickham (1890-1965), circa 1913-1944; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Two letters are written from China, one from Chefoo [present day Yantai] and the second from Tsingtao, while her husband, Captain Williams C. Wickham (1887-1985) was serving in the U.S. Asiatic Fleet.
  - Family correspondence of Credilla Miller Wickham (1890-1965), wife of Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985) chiefly to her mother – numbered letters on board a ship traveling to Japan, China, and the Philippines with her family, [1924?]; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Family correspondence of Credilla Miller Wickham (1890-1965), wife of Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985), February through August, chiefly to her mother, while her husband was serving in the U.S. Asiatic Fleet aboard the U.S.S. Pillsbury at Chefoo, China [present day Yantai], [1924-1927?]; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Family correspondence of Credilla Miller Wickham (1890-1965), wife of Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985), September through October, chiefly to her mother, [1924-1927?]; 1 folder(s) (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Family correspondence of Credilla Miller Wickham (1890-1965), wife of Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985), November through December, chiefly to her mother, [1924-1927?]; 1 folder(s) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Family correspondence of Elise Warwick Barksdale Wickham (1861-1952), wife of Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943), chiefly to her husband, Henry, 1883-1910; 1 folder(s) (Box 8, Folder 2)
    One letter from Williams Carter Wickham expresses his pleasure at her engagement to his son, Henry Taylor Wickham (August 26, 1885).
  - Family correspondence of Elise Warwick Barksdale Wickham (1861-1952), wife of Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943), 1911-1925; 1 folder(s) (Box 8, Folder 3)
    These letters are chiefly to her husband, Henry, while staying at the Homestead, Hot Springs, Virginia, (1911) and White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia (1913) for her health but two letters are to her son, Captain Williams Carter Wickham during his journey to join the Asiastic fleet (1924).
  - Family correspondence of George Barksdale Wickham (1888-1928) and Virginia Wickham, circa 1896-1937; 1 folder(s) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Family Correspondence of Harriet M. Wickham, chiefly written from Mattituck, Long Island, to her cousin, William F. Wickham, 1870-1878; 1 folder(s) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Family Correspondence of Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943), as a young boy and while attending Washington College, Lexington, Virginia, beginning in 1864, and including some letters from his sister, Annie Wickham, 1853-1860, 1864; 1 folder(s) (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Early letters are chiefly from his grandparents, William F. and Anne Wickham, and the letters in 1864 are between Henry and his parents, Williams C. and Lucy Wickham
  - Family Correspondence of Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943), while attending Washington College, Lexington, Virginia, chiefly with grandparents and parents; his grandmother's last letter to him, was dated December, 18, 1867, 3 folders, 1865-1867; 3 folder(s) (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
  - Family Correspondence of Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943), 1868-1915; 1 folder(s) (Box 8, Folder 10)
    One letter mentions the death of his grandmother, Anne B. Carter Wickham (February 26, 1868); four letters were written as a University of Virginia student (October 17, 24, and 31, 1869; and May 8, 1870); and one letter from Henry to his son, Captain Williams C. Wickham, congratulating him on his engagement to Credilla Miller (October 2, 1911).
  - Family correspondence of Brigadier J.C. Wickham, England, with Captain Williams C. Wickham, chiefly about genealogy, 1953-1957; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Family Correspondence of Janet Anna Jane Wickham, wife of Hill Dawe Wickham, with William F. Wickham, 1875; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Family Correspondence of Jerusha Wickham (1815-1901), Southold, Long Island, with her cousin, William F. Wickham, 1874-1878; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Family Correspondence of John Wickham (1825-1892), son of Edmund Wickham and Lucy Carter, who became a judge in St. Louis, Missouri, and writes as a student at the University of Virginia, 1846, 1840-1862; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 4)
    John Wickham writes concerning land in Franklin County, Missouri, belonging to the estate of John Wickham (July 11, 1850).
  - Family Correspondence of John Wickham (1825-1892), son of Edmund Wickham and Lucy Carter, who became a judge in St. Louis, Missouri, 1868-1877, 1888; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Family Correspondence of John Wickham (1822-1847), chiefly with his parents, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) and Anne Butler Carter Wickham (1797-1868), 1840-1847; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Family correspondence of Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham (1821-1909), 1834-1877; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Family Correspondence of Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913), 1854-1910; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Family Correspondence of Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) with her father-in-law, William F. Wickham, and her mother-in-law, Anne Butler Carter Wickham, 1848-1876; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Family correspondence of Maclurg Wickham (1814-1900), chiefly with his brother, William F. Wickham, 1871-1877; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Apparently the spelling of his name varies slightly from his mother's family name, Maclurg versus McClurg, but the use here reflects the spelling on his grave stone.
  - Family Correspondence of Robert C. Wickham (1823-1847), nephew of William F. Wickham and surgeon in the U.S. Army, 1846; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Family Correspondence of W. Leigh Wickham (1828-1889), nephew of William F. Wickham, 1848-1863, 1888; 1 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 12)
    During the Civil War, Leigh Wickham received an appointment in the Confederate Quartermaster department at Memphis, Tennessee (September 13 and 19, and December 8, 1861); reports that the people of Mississippi were frightened of General Grant's army (December 23, 1862); and mentions the hanging of Colonel Lawrence Orton Williams as a Confederate spy by the Federals (June 14, 1863).
  - Family correspondence of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) with his wife, Anne Butler Carter Wickham (1797-1868), 2 folders, 1849-[1865], and undated; 2 folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 13-14)
  - Family correspondence of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) with his brother, Edmund F. Wickham (1796-1843), 1817-1842; 1 folder(s) (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Correspondence includes one letter from Williams Carter Wickham while at the University of Virginia concerning the results of Professor Rogers' analysis of Edmund's specimens of marl (January 16, 1838).
  - Family correspondence of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) with his brother, James McClurg Wickham (1802-1850, 1830-1842; 1 folder(s) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Family correspondence of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) with his brother, John Wickham (1825-1902), 2 folders, 1848-1877; 2 folder(s) (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
  - Family correspondence of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) and his wife, Anne Butler Carter Wickham (1797-1868), with their two sons, Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) and John Wickham (1822-1847) while they were attending the Howard School for boys, near Alexandria, Virginia, 4 folders, 1832-1834; 4 folder(s) (Box 10, Folder 5-8)
    The Howard School opened in 1831 and continued until 1834 with two teachers, the Reverend Jonathan Loring Woart (1807-1838) and his brother, the Reverend John Woart. The Episcopal High School opened in 1839 on the former Howard School location. There are also letters from the Reverend Jonathan Loring Woart (1807-1838) to William F. Wickham, including progress reports on the two boys, among this correspondence.
  - Family correspondence of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), 1858-1879; 1 folder(s) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Family Correspondence of W.F. Wickham, Jr. (1830-185[0?]), nephew of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), 1848-1850; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Contains two letters from W.F. Wickham, Jr. as a student at the University of Virginia (December 19, 1848 and January 12, 1849).
  - Family correspondence of William Fanning Wickham, Jr., (1860-1900), son of Williams Carter Wickham and Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham, 2 folders, 1870-1883; 2 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
    Includes letters written as a student at the Episcopal High School of Virginia, Fairfax, Virginia (1874-1878) and the University of Virginia (1878-1883).
  - Family correspondence of Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his father, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), and his mother, Anne Butler Carter Wickham (1797-1868), 1845-1859; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 4)
    While his father is away in New York and Boston, Williams Carter Wickham sends reports on the activities and condition of the plantation, including illness and death among the slaves (September 7, 1845; September 15, 1848). Williams Carter Wickham writes with further reports to his father hoping to catch him still at Bowling Green (August 30, 1849); and Williams describes a trip with his wife Lucy to New York and on to Quebec (August 27, 1855).
  - Family correspondence of Williams Carter Wickham with his father, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), and his mother, Anne Butler Carter Wickham (1797-1868), 1861; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 5)
    This folder contains references to the participation of Williams Carter Wickham in the First Battle of Bull Run (July 24, 1861, and August 1861); rumors of possible attacks on Arlington and Alexandria and Norfolk (September 2, 1861); discussion about the ramifications of the seizure of James Murray Mason and John Slidell on board the RMS Trent by Union Captain Charles Wilkes (December 8, 1861); and W. Leigh Wickham's commission as assistant quartermaster with rank of captain (December 20, 1861). During the recent visit of William F. Wickham with General Robert E. Lee, Lee reported on the sufferings of the army in the west [1861].
  - Family correspondence of Williams Carter Wickham with his father, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), and his mother, Anne Butler Carter Wickham (1797-1868), 1862-1865; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Williams Carter Wickham shares his weariness of the war and announces himself as a candidate for Congress (May 15, 1863); William F. Wickham voices his concern over scarcity of food in Richmond and near Charlottesville to Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (January 19, 1864); and William F. Wickham fears that Lee cannot maintain communications to the south and wishes he had nothing more to do with land or slaves if only his son were home in peace (June 28, [1864]).
  - Family correspondence of Williams Carter Wickham with his father, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), 1870-1875; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, 1858-1860; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, chiefly concerning home and extended family matters during the early part of the Civil War, 1861 January-July; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 9)
    This folder contains references to the participation of Williams Carter Wickham in the First Battle of Bull Run (July 22-23, 27, and 31, 1861).
  - Family correspondence – Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) with his wife, Lucy Penn Taylor Wickham (1830-1913) and young children, 1861 August-October; 1 folder(s) (Box 11, Folder 10)